making Aviation green is a huge
challenge flying is such a big part of
our lives and we have to balance that
with the fact that it contributes hugely
to global warming we've left it a long
time we've now got a very short window
within which we need to get emissions
from this sector down to nearly zero we
need to be throwing everything at this
problem that we can think
of there are two big reasons why
Aviation presents a unique challenge in
terms of climate change the first is
that more and more people are flying and
the second is that flying remains almost
totally dependent on fossil fuels we
haven't got green technologies available
yet for the aviation
[Music]
sector and that's roughly equivalent to
the total emissions from the UK and
Germany
combined in 2019 Airlines Carri around
4.5 billion passengers on flight and
we're really expecting that to
[Music]
grow globally just 1% of the population
many of whom are frequent flyers
generate half of all emissions from the
aviation
sector
there is no Silver Bullet to get
Aviation to become green but rather a
whole set of different options each with
pros and
cons winglets are vertical looking
extensions that we've uh added at the
end of the Wings and what they do is to
increase the efficiency of the Wings
these winglets were inspired by birds
and we are currently looking at much
more features from bird wings and bird
flight and incorporating them into our
aircraft the aviation industry is really
good at making itself more efficient
through a mixture of improving
technology and learning to fly the
aircraft more efficiently if you look at
uh history we are improving the
efficiency of our aircraft at about 2%
per year that uh is definitely very
little and it cannot continue forever so
we definitely need to uh change our
aircraft
fuels jet engines at the moment run on
fuel made from fossil fuels so it's
really important that we find ways to
replace that in aircraft biofuels are a
form of fuel which is made from
plant-based materials the one possible
example is vegetable oil which exist in
in very large quantities and uh can be
transformed into a
[Music]
biofuel for instance if we were to
replace the entire jet fuel used in the
UK with biofuels we would be using about
68% of the land that we currently use to
grow our food another possibility is
what we call E fuels which is scrubbing
the carbon dioxide from the air and
putting it through chemical processes
that turn it back into jet fuel again so
it turns into a circular process where
it's all going into the atmosphere and
then coming back out again one big
disadvantage of e fuels is that they are
very expensive not only in terms of
their cost but also in terms of the
energy that they
use hydrogen is a gas that if you react
it with the oxygen in the air can
release a lot of energy that makes it
potentially a really good aviation fuel
but it's not without its problems uh for
a start we can't store it in the current
designs of airlanes secondly at the
moment about 95% of our hydrogen comes
from fossil fuels hydrogen is very um
explosive which poses serious uh safety
considerations designing manufacturing
and Licensing hydrogen power aircraft is
something that is bound to take decades
and cost in the regions of tens of
billions of
pounds electric airplanes are still
incredibly rare so I'm one of the very
few people in the world who has had a
chance to Pilot an electric
airplane
whilst it's possible to make an electric
car that works well if you put those
same batteries into an airplane it's
simply too heavy to
fly there's no doubt that it's going to
take a lot of resources particularly
energy it's going to cost a lot and it's
going to require a huge amount of effort
from business and from government
working together with the corporation
and support of the public it would be
great if there was one kind of fix it
all solution that we could put in place
for this sector uh
unfortunately uh we're going to have to
do everything we can think of and it's
all probably going to be quite
challenging a lot of the technologies
that we need for Greening Aviation are
still some decades apart they are very
expensive and the electric energy that
would be required uh from a renewable
source will also be uh very expensive
and time consuming to set Place
alongside that just as importantly we're
probably going to have to fly less
because we've left it so long that just
isn't time left the aircraft coming off
the production line today will probably
still be flying in 2050 which is the
date by which we have to be at net zero
emissions we need to be building the
kind of society in which there are good
alternatives to Flying so if you choose
to take a holiday domestically in your
own country that will start to create
that kind of demand that will help make
a more sustainable future
do you
fly I last took a flight before my
daughter was born and she's going to be
a teenager this
summer